# Rodrigo Cortés Sánchez

**BSc.** Mechatronics **Engineering** Software Engineer

□ rodrigo.cortess@outlook.com

(+34) 623 27 43 92



Valladolid 2, 08014 Barcelona, Spain



www.linkedin.com/in/rodrigo-cortes-s



www.github.com/rcrtss

# Objective

I intend to consolidate my knowledge and identify future opportunities at the intersection of Artificial Intelligence and Robotics, specializing in Edge AI and Physical AI. In the long-term I see myself leading teams of engineers in AI applications, in relevant private or public organizations and hopefully my own company, while building an academic career.

## Academic Background

## Universidad Anáhuac Norte, Mexico

Bachelor of engineering, Mechatronics Engineering Aug. 2015 to May 2020 GPA 9.13/10.00 (Equivalent to 7.53 in Spain)

Ranked among the top 5 students in my cohort

# L'École Nationale d'Ingénieurs De Tarbes, France

European Project Semester, Mechanical Engineering (30 ECTS)

Feb. 2019 to Jun. 2019

Development of a software solution for an autonomous mobile robot to follow a person while avoiding obstacles, using embedded sensors and computer vision.

16.74/20 - outstanding performance | 24 ECTS Ranked highest among all projects in that semester

## Extra-academic Courses and Certificates

#### MIT Profesional Education Nov. 2024

Applied Data Science Program: AI for Effective Decision Making

- Intensive 12-week program on applied data science, ML and Al
- Capstone Project: Hybrid Music Recommendation System [F1@k: 0.51]
- 16 Continuing Education Units (CEUs)

#### Other

- EILTS Academic English Certificate ETS (C1)
- Machine Learning with Python | Coursera (IBM)
- Deep Learning & Neural Networks with Keras | Coursera (IBM)
- Programming with Google Go Specialization | Coursera
- Intro. to FPGA Design for Embedded Systems | Coursera

## Other Activities

#### Speaker - Mechatronics Conference Days Nov. 2024

Presentation on a scalable architecture for smart energy distribution systems using edge computing and microservices in embedded platforms.

## CV Assistant App Nov. 2023 to Sep. 2024

Development of a desktop application that uses LLMs to populate a DOCX template from a provided PDF CV, simplifying the process for headhunters. Technologies used: Python, LangChain, PySide.

### Inderect Calorimetry Cage Aug. 2018 to May 2020

Research project focused on an indirect calorimetry cage prototype designed to measure heat production in laboratory rats. Received third place in Anahuac's research poster contest (10th edition) for the undergraduate

## **Eigenvalue Problem for Vibration Analysis** *Sep. 2018*

Presentation on an application of the eigenvalue problem for vibration analysis (co-author). URL:

https://www.smm.org.mx/resumen\_semblanza.php?t=res&id=1694

# **Professional Experience**

#### **Software Engineer**

Circontrol (BCN) | Jun. 2023 to Present

- Developed software for smart electrical power distribution systems.
- Designed and implemented an Energy Management System for smart buildings.
- Built and deployed microservices using Golang, Docker CLI and Docker Compose.
- Developed a system for device interoperability for MQTT, Modbus, REST, and gRPC.
- Applied Clean Architecture, TDD, DDD and SOLID principles.
- Researched new technologies and architectures for IoT and Edge Computing.

#### **R&D Embedded Software Engineer**

BSV. Electronic (BCN) | Jul. 2022 to Jun. 2023

- Designed software and hardware for pool automation systems.
- Developed MCU firmware in C and C++ for STM32 (Cortex M4) and ESP32.
- Integrated cost-efficient embedded solutions to enhance performance.
- Optimized system architecture, improving efficiency in real-time systems.

## Software Development Engineer C++

Altair Engineering (CDMX) | Nov. 2020 to Feb. 2022

- Developed core features for HyperWorks using C++.
- Improved software stability by identifying and fixing critical bugs.
- Managed software development cycle and version control.

## Junior Network and Transportation Engineer

Traxión Logistics (CDMX) | Apr. 2020 to Nov. 2020

- Optimized transportation routes through data analysis, reducing costs.
- Developed dashboards to identify and capitalize on operational opportunities.
- · Implemented data pipelines for real-time metric tracking.
- Collaborated with clients to offer customized logistic solutions to fit their needs.

# Tools and Technologies

- Programming Languages: C/C++, Python, Go, Java, R, Shell
- Data Libriaries: Keras, Numpy, Pandas
- Al Libraries: LangChain, OpenAl, OpenCV, CUDA (HW acceleration)
- IoT Frameworks: EdgeX Foundry
- Embedded: Jetson Nano, RaspberryPI, ESP32, STM32, PIC16, atmega328
- Version Control: Git, GitHub, GitLab, Perforce
- Architectures: Microservices (Docker), Ports and Adapters
- Communication Protocols: MQTT, Modbus, REST, CAN, gRPC
- IDEs: Visual Studio, VS Code, Codeblocks, vim
- Scientific Programing: Labview, MatLab & Simulink, Mathematica
- Project Management: Redmine, Jira, Confluence
- · Operating Systems: Linux (Ubuntu), Windows

### **Hard Skills**

- Embedded Systems
- IoT and Edge Computing
- Data Structures and Algorithms
- Robotics and Control Theory
- Statistics and Machine Learning
- Engineering design
- High and Low Level Design

#### Soft Skills

- Assertive Communication
- Problem Solving
- Critical Thinking
- Presentation Skills
- Teamwork
- Leadership
- Adaptability

#### Languages

- Spanish: Native
- English: C1
- German: A2
- French: A2

#### Other Interests

- Drums/Percussions and Electric Guitar
- Music Technology and Audio
- Philosophy
- Scuba Diving